<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://immsrini.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://immsrini.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2024-03-14T05:54:09+00:00</updated><id>https://immsrini.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Mukundhan Srinivasan</title><subtitle>Mukund&apos;s space between the manifolds </subtitle><entry><title type="html">lecture on Artha Panchakam</title><link href="https://immsrini.github.io/blog/2024/lecture-on-Artha-Panchakam/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="lecture on Artha Panchakam"/><published>2024-02-25T16:40:16+00:00</published><updated>2024-02-25T16:40:16+00:00</updated><id>https://immsrini.github.io/blog/2024/lecture%20on%20Artha%20Panchakam</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://immsrini.github.io/blog/2024/lecture-on-Artha-Panchakam/"><![CDATA[<p>Adiyen was presented with an opportunity to address a ghosti of bakthas and was instructed to share a few things on Artha Panchakam. You can find the YouTube video <a href="https://youtu.be/UFxAaethpn8">here</a>.</p> <p>Needless to mention, adiyen is no vedic scholar and always learning along with everyone.</p> <iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/UFxAaethpn8?si=j3TXypBNWUEjDlub&amp;start=1" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen=""></iframe> <p>-dAsan</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="vedic"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[notes on the five for mumukshus]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">DPO v. PPO</title><link href="https://immsrini.github.io/blog/2023/DPO_bestPaper_Neurips/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="DPO v. PPO"/><published>2023-12-28T11:00:16+00:00</published><updated>2023-12-28T11:00:16+00:00</updated><id>https://immsrini.github.io/blog/2023/DPO_bestPaper_Neurips</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://immsrini.github.io/blog/2023/DPO_bestPaper_Neurips/"><![CDATA[<p>Given the complexity and specificity of Direct Preference Optimization (DPO) and Proximal Policy Optimization (PPO) in the context of Large Language Models (LLMs), it’s important to delve into recent research and developments to provide an accurate and detailed report. Here’s an overview:</p> <h4 id="direct-preference-optimization-dpo-in-llms">Direct Preference Optimization (DPO) in LLMs</h4> <p>Overview:</p> <p>Direct Preference Optimization is a method used to align the outputs of models like LLMs with human preferences or specified criteria. This method involves collecting human feedback on model outputs and directly optimizing the model to produce outputs that are more aligned with these preferences.</p> <p>Key Features:</p> <p>Human-in-the-loop: DPO relies heavily on human feedback, making it particularly suitable for tasks where human judgment is crucial. Alignment with Preferences: This method is effective in fine-tuning models to adhere to nuanced human preferences, ethics, or cultural norms.</p> <p>Examples and Research:</p> <p>A significant example of this approach is in fine-tuning language models for tasks like generating more ethical or unbiased content. Research papers like “Learning to Summarize with Human Feedback” (OpenAI) illustrate the use of human feedback in optimizing language models.</p> <h4 id="proximal-policy-optimization-ppo-in-llms">Proximal Policy Optimization (PPO) in LLMs</h4> <p>Overview:</p> <p>PPO is a reinforcement learning algorithm that’s been adapted for fine-tuning LLMs, particularly in decision-making or interactive scenarios. The algorithm is known for its stability and effectiveness in a variety of environments, making it a strong choice for fine-tuning language models.</p> <p>Key Features:</p> <p>Stable and Efficient Learning: PPO is designed to avoid large policy updates, which can destabilize training. Broad Applicability: The algorithm can be applied to a variety of tasks, from game playing to conversational agents.</p> <p>Examples and Research:</p> <p>An application of PPO in LLMs could be in interactive systems like chatbots, where the model learns to optimize its responses based on rewards. “Proximal Policy Optimization Algorithms” (Schulman et al., 2017) provides foundational knowledge on PPO’s mechanics and applications.</p> <h4 id="comparison-and-analysis">Comparison and Analysis</h4> <ol> <li> <p>Suitability for LLMs: DPO is particularly suited for tasks where alignment with complex human preferences and judgments is crucial. PPO, on the other hand, excels in environments where a clear reward signal can guide the optimization of responses or actions.</p> </li> <li> <p>Challenges and Limitations: DPO’s reliance on human feedback makes it resource-intensive and potentially biased based on the feedback sample. PPO, while efficient, might not capture the nuanced preferences that human feedback can provide, as seen in DPO.</p> </li> <li> <p>Choosing Between DPO and PPO: The choice between DPO and PPO depends on the specific requirements of the task at hand. For applications requiring adherence to complex human values or preferences, DPO might be preferable. For scenarios where there are clear reward structures and the need for efficient learning, PPO could be more suitable.</p> </li> </ol> <h4 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h4> <p>Both DPO and PPO offer unique advantages in the context of fine-tuning LLMs, with their suitability depending on the specific goals and constraints of the application. DPO excels in aligning model outputs with nuanced human preferences, while PPO offers a more general and efficient approach to optimizing model behavior in interactive scenarios.</p> <p>For a deeper understanding and more specific insights, consulting the latest research papers and case studies in these areas is highly recommended.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="MachineLearning"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Clearly one one winner here]]></summary></entry></feed>